Okay, and happy daylight savings time, I guess. So we're in דף
כ"ז. Daf Chaf-Zayin. We start on the משנה Mishnah at the bottom
of כ"ו עמוד ב'. Chaf-Vav Amud-Bet. And we are looking at an
interesting debate about רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and חכמים, Chachamim, now we're
going to find out it's רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, about making something,
making a statement whether it all takes place at once or sequentially,
and how you can distinguish the mother from the fetus when you
sanctify an animal. So let's take a look at our משנה. Mishnah.
הרי זו תמורת עולה תמורת שלמים. Harei zo tmurat olah, tmurat shelamim.
Let's say instead of just trying to distinguish between the mother and
the fetus like we have done before, here what you actually did
was you said two things about the same animal. Behold this is
a תמורה tmurah of an עולה olah and a תמורה tmurah of
a שלמים. shelamim. Now presumably as we're going to find out later,
it's actually quite fascinating that in this entire מסכת masechet we have
yet to find out exactly the formula and the way in which
one does the act of תמורה. tmurah. That's coming at the end
of this פרק. perek. And we're going to find out that's a
little late, but anyway, we're going to find out that as we've
been assuming all along, but just to reiterate, that you need the
animal that you're attempting to transfer the קדושה kedushah from, the one
that has the original קדושה, kedushah, to be in front of you.
So assuming in front of you you have an עולה olah and
a שלמים shelamim and you take another animal that's חולין chullin and
you say this is a תמורה tmurah for the עולה, olah, it's
a תמורה tmurah for the שלמים. shelamim. Okay, so not generic עולה
שלמים Olah Shlamim but a specific one, but you said both. Well,
which one? So הרי זו תמורת עולה דברי רבי מאיר. harei zo
tmurat olah, divrei Rabbi Meir. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is consistent.
He says your words take effect sequentially and therefore it becomes a
תמורת עולה. tmurat olah. Once it's a תמורת עולה, tmurat olah, it
cannot become a תמורת שלמים. tmurat shelamim. That's what it is, end
of story, it's an עולה. olah אמר רבי יוסי, Amar Rabbi Yose,
so רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose said like we said yesterday, אם לכך
נתכוון תחילה, im le-kach nitkaven techilah, if that was his original intent,
so to say both, behold he actually called ב' שמות כאחת, base
shemos ke-achas, you can't say two things at once, you have to
speak sequentially. So even though you said it sequentially, if you meant
that it should be both, so דבריו
קיימים, devarav kayamim, it's both, it's like a hybrid, it's a תמורת
עולה tmurat olah and a שלמים, shelamim which means what? Which means
that it has קדושת עולה קדושת שלמים. kedushat olah, kedushat shelamim. You
wait for it to graze, you redeem it, and with the proceeds
you use half of the money to buy an עולה, olah. half
of the money to buy a שלמים. shelamim, So it has both
קדושות. kedushas. ואם משאמר תמורת עולה נמלך ואמר תמורת שלמים, Ve-im mishe-amar
tmurat olah nimlach ve-amar tmurat shelamim,
but if after you said תמורת עולה tmurat olah you actually changed
your mind with a new thought, then I agree with you, הרי
זו תמורת עולה, harei zo tmurat olah, that is a תמורה tmurah
of an עולה. olah, So it's exactly like the debate they had
before between רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, here
too they are debating that. Okay, whether it's sequentially or at the
same time. Yes?
So I guess we're going to learn what the consequences of having
both קדושות kedushas are at the same time.
Okay. But for now the simple assumption is that it is you
redeem it and you use half the proceeds for an עולה olah.
and half the proceeds for a שלמים. shelamim. It's not like a
hundred percent both. I mean, it's essentially even if you try to
do a hundred percent both, the effect is fifty percent of each.
Okay, because it can't be a hundred percent one and a hundred
percent the other. Okay, let's take a look now at the גמרא,
Gemara, top of כ"ו עמוד א'. Chaf-Vav Amud-Aleph. אמר רבי יצחק בר
יוסף אמר רבי יוחנן הכל מודים, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar Yosef, amar
Rabbi Yochanan, hakol modim, now until
although we have thought that what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir was trying
to was saying was a categorical position that it always takes place
effect sequentially, he's going to say that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir actually
there are times that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir agrees to רבי יוסי.
Rabbi Yose.
So and so here he's going to frame the debate. Let's take
a look. הכל מודים באומר תחול זו ואחר כך תחול זו דברי
הכל תפס ראשון. Hakol modim be-omer tachal zo ve-achar kach tachal zo,
divrei hakol tafas rishon. First of all, there are times רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yose agrees to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, if you're explicit. If
you say first I want it to be a תמורת עולה, tmurat
olah, then I want it to be a תמורת שלמים. tmurat shelamim.
So you specifically say I want it to take effect sequentially, then
of course, first thing that happened was עולה olah and then it's
too late for the next thing to happen. Everybody agrees that the
first thing was effective and not the second. Now if you say
לא
תחול זו אלא אם כן חלה זו, lo tachal zo ela im
ken chalsah zo,
let's say you explicitly said I want it to happen sequentially. I
want this to be a תמורת עולה tmurat olah only if and
when it also becomes a תמורת שלמים. tmurat shelamim. Okay, so you're
very explicit that you want it to both happen sequentially, then תרוייהו
קדשי, travaihu kadshi, then it has both קדושות, kedushas, everybody agrees. So
meaning also, and here's something that I might not have realized, nobody
disagrees that it's possible to have both קדושות, kedushas, to be a
hybrid קדושה. kedushah. Before I knew it was possible, it was the
mother and the fetus, and the only question was what was the
effect of your words. Here you might have disagreed with the whole
status at the end, but no, everybody agrees if you're explicit that
can also work.
לא נחלקו אלא כגון משנתנו, Lo nechelku ela kegon mishnasenu, they only
disagree when you did not you weren't explicit like in our משנה.
Mishnah. דאמר תמורת עולה תמורת שלמים. De-amar tmurat olah tmurat shelamim. You
just said you said them sequentially but you weren't explicit what you
meant. דרבי מאיר סבר, De-Rabbi Meir savar, now you would have thought
that here רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is just saying, okay, I have
a categorical position, תפס לשון ראשון. tafas lashon rishon. But here he's
no, he's actually going to say רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir wouldn't always
say that. מדיהוה ליה למימר תמורת עולה ושלמים, Mi-de-hava lei le-meimar tmurat
olah ve-shelamim,
you could have phrased your words differently. You could have said תמורת
עולה ושלמים. tmurat olah ve-shelamim. That would have been explicit that you
meant both of them at the same time. And
rather ואמר תמורת עולה. ve-amar tmurat olah. תמורת עולה שלמים. tmuras ola
shlomim. Okay, so since you repeated the word תמורה, tmura, הוה ליה
למימר תחת זבח זה תחת זבח זה. havah lei lemaimar tachas zevech
zeh tachas zevech zeh.
We're going to read your words to say first A and then
B because that extra word points to us that you mean first
A and then B. ורבי יוסי סבר, v'Rabbi Yossi savar, and Rabbi
Yossi says no, אי אמר תמורת עולה, ee amar tmuras ola, there's
a reason why maybe you stuck in the extra word. Because had
you just said תמורת עולה ושלמים, tmuras ola v'shlomim, if you just
said תמורה tmura of עולה olah and שלמים, shelamim. which would have
been more explicit hybrid, הוה אמינא קדושה ואינה קריבה. havah amina kedoshah
v'einah kreivah. I would have, you would have thought, not הוה אמינא,
havah amina, more like you would have thought that that would have
been half and half and you would have known you wouldn't be
able to bring it as a קרבן. korban. But you in your
head actually thought there was a difference between saying I want it
to be a hybrid 50% each or I want it to be
100% each. In your mind you thought that if you were going
to make it 100% תמורת עולה tmuras ola and 100% תמורת שלמים
tmuras shlomim and you would have been able to brought a קרבן
korban and you would have got double credit. I now brought a
קרבן korban that was an עולה ola and a שלמים. shlomim, Okay,
that's the משוגעת meshugaas you were thinking in your head. You didn't
realize, okay, but that's why you said the word תמורה tmura second
time. If you would have explicitly said, if you would have said
תמורת עולה ושלמים, tmuras ola v'shlomim, you would have realized that you're
making it a 50% one, 50% the other and there's no such
thing as a hybrid קרבן. korban. You thought you were going to
do a double קרבן. korban. So that's why you said it. So
that's what you were thinking. Okay, wonderful, that's what you're thinking. But
you didn't mean sequentially and we're not going to interpret your words
sequentially. Thank you. קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, so therefore we're
going to interpret your words that you meant that you meant both
and both take effect. So according to this, what we're saying is
is that there are times where although Rabbi Meir is let's say
predisposed to interpret your words sequentially, there are times based not if
you're explicit of course he'd agree, but there are times where based
on the way you phrase it he might be willing to to
agree that you really meant you really meant simultaneous not sequential. Now
that doesn't really fit with the previous Rabbi Meir's because the previous
cases if you remember Rabbi Meir said I want the mother to
be a שלמים shlomim. and the ולד vlad to be an עולה.
ola Well there you didn't have any other words you could have
used so let's not and why not interpret the whole thing to
mean simultaneously? Why interpret it sequentially according to this? So תוספות Tosafos
says תוספות Tosafos tries to find a way to say yeah you're
right there there
because those statements are not contradictory, right, we will more we will
interpret them sequentially. First you meant A and then B. You didn't
realize that once you made the mother שלמים shlomim it would prevent
the ולד vlad from being an עולה. ola. But because anyway the
concepts are not contradictory we'll interpret them sequentially, that is Rabbi Meir's
predisposition. But here what we're saying is is that since תמורת עולה
tmuras ola and תמורת שלמים tmuras shlomim are contradiction, here Rabbi Meir
is more willing to sort of say that you know how could
you have meant contradictory things? He's more try would be willing to
consider the idea that you meant somehow a hybrid and sequential. Okay
so that's a very sort of you know a subtle qualification within
Rabbi Meir. Yes Rabbi Meir is predisposed to always say you mean
sequential, we interpret your words sequentially A and then B. Here however
he might be willing to concede it that you meant at the
same time but again because of the terminology you used he's once
again going to say you meant sequentially. Yes.
Would they have the same debate to makshish it to begin with
if I said I want this to be in effect תמורה, tmura,
but if I said מחצית... machatzis... Oh שלמים. shlomim Yeah.
Yeah
definitely.
So although there yeah. Other words.
Yeah. No let's go with that for now. I mean I do
actually believe that there are cases like that that it's explicitly said
that. Although it is interesting why
it gave the scenario of saying תמורה tmura this תמורה tmura that.
I mean we are in תמורה. tmura.
Right.
Right I understand.
Okay. Alright. So anyway so although so fine Rabbi so this statement
of רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak in the name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan says that maybe Rabbi Meir might agree if the if it
was worded slightly differently but again the general assumption is that Rabbi
Meir doesn't have any anything to do with wording he always says
they just take effect sequentially. Let's take a look as the גמרא
Gemara continues. תנו
רבנן. tanu rabbanan. האומר בהמה זו חציה תמורת עולה וחציה תמורת שלמים.
ha'omer beheima zu chatziha tmuras ola v'chatziha tmuras shlomim. Let's say you
said half and half. כולה תעשה עולה דברי רבי מאיר. kula tei'asei
ola divrei Rabbi Meir. So once again Rabbi Meir says it's all
an עולה. ola. So again here you would have said oh well
that sounds pretty clear like you wanted to do a hybrid and
nevertheless so this again sort of is what you know is why
you really have to narrow the original statement the statement we just
read which is that sometimes Rabbi Meir would agree. Because here it
really seems like Rabbi Meir is categorical. Whatever you said first that's
what takes effect. So why so okay so let it only be
half. No because if you remember we have a general principle that
if you sanctify a part of the animal certainly a part that
the life is dependent on, some say even any part of the
animal, the whole animal becomes a קרבן. korban. So if you really
did say a half and that took effect first that would have
transferred the whole thing into an עולה. ola. So again Rabbi Meir
is really saying that you just your words take effect sequentially and
if half of it became an עולה ola. the whole thing became
an עולה. ola וחכמים אומרים, v'Chachamim omrim, the חכמים, Chachamim, until now
we said Rabbi Yossi, here's the חכמים Chachamim say... Here are תירעה
כשתסתאב ותימכר, tira kishitsta’ev vetimacher, we'll let it graze until it gets
a מום moom and then sell it, ויביא בדמי חציו עולה ובדמי
חציו שלמים, veyavi bidmei chetzyo olah uvidmei chetzyo shelamim, he'd use half
the money for an עולה, ola. half the money for a שלמים.
shlomim. So they basically say your entire statement takes effect at the
same time, not sequentially. אמר רבי יוסי, Amar Rebbe Yosi, said רבי
יוסי, Rebbe Yosi, אם לכך נתכוון מתחילה, im lekach nitkaven mitchila, if
you had originally intended to say both, to
say like you know it all at the same time, you wanted
one unified statement, then דבריו קיימים, devarav kayamim, then it's valid. ואי
אפשר לו להוציא שתי שמות כאחת, ve'ee efshar lo lehotzi shtei shemot
ke'achat, since you can't say, you have to speak sequentially, you can't
say all the words at the same time, so דבריו קיימים, devarav
kayamim, so it takes effect and it's half and half. So
okay, that's what he says. So now the גמרא Gemara says, רבי
יוסי היינו רבנן, Rebbe Yosi hainu rabanan, isn't that exactly what the
rabbis just said, that it's half and half? So the גמרא Gemara
says, yeah okay fine, you're right. כולה רבי יוסי קתני לה, kula
Rebbe Yosi katani la, you're right, it's not the חכמים chachamim and
רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi that's there, it's that we're now saying this
חכמים chachamim really is the position of רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi and
רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi explicates the logic of saying it all takes
effect at the same time and not sequentially because as human beings
we speak sequentially. Okay, תניא אידך, tanya idach, we've learned in another
ברייתא. braita.
Considerably easier than the last few days, huh? בהמה חציה עולה וחציה
חטאת, behema chetzya olah vechetzya chatat,
let's say you say this animal, here you go Michael's case, although
you didn't say עולה וחטאת, olah vechatat, you said half and half.
Anyway, you said half עולה olah, half חטאת. chatat. קרב עולה דברי
רבי מאיר. karev olah divrei Rebbe Meir. So again רבי מאיר Rebbe
Meir says it takes place sequentially, as soon as you said half
עולה olah the whole thing becomes an עולה, olah when you said
half חטאת chatat nothing happened. רבי יוסי אומר תמות, Rebbe Yosi omer
tamut, it has to die. Why? Because it is a half חטאת.
chatat. Since when does a half חטאת chatat die? I mean even
if right, since when does a חטאת chatat die? So רש״י Rashi
says it's a חטאת chatat that you're not obligated in and you
don't have a חטא. chet. So therefore since when, so okay fine.
So we've never said that if you're מקדיש makdish a חטאת chatat
even if you're not obligated that the animal has to die. So
תוספות Tosafot says okay really he has a different גירסא, girsa, he
quotes the תוספתא Tosefta and the תוספתא's Tosefta גירסא girsa is חציה
תמורת עולה וחציה תמורת חטאת. chetzya tmurat olah vechetzya tmurat chatat. We're
back to the תמורה tmura case. And if it's a תמורת חטאת,
tmurat chatat, then תמורת חטאת tmurat chatat is מתה. mesa. Okay, so
therefore here until now we sort of assumed like you know רבי
יוסי Rebbe Yosi was more you know maybe reasonable, but we should
point out that even if you're more reasonable it doesn't mean you're
more lenient. I mean if you take for example the case even
before we get to תמות, tamut, רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir allowed you
to bring this as a קרבן, korban, he said it was an
עולה, olah, and רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi made you wait to graze
till it got a מום, moom, right? Now in the last משנה,
mishna, רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir let you, you know, רבי יוסי Rebbe
Yosi let you do what you wanted to do. Bring the mother
as one thing, the fetus as another. רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir said
no you tripped yourself up, the fetus is defined by the mother.
And so but it's not a question of lenient or not lenient,
you know, sometimes the consequences work out better one way, sometimes the
other way. In this case if you said half תמורת עולה tmurat
olah half תמורת חטאת. tmurat chatat. Then according to רבי יוסי, Rebbe
Yosi, תמורת חטאת tmurat chatat takes effect at least halfway and that
defines then the whole animal is מתה. mesa. For part of the
animal we say מתה, mesa, we say it for the whole animal.
Yes, Charlie?
Why can't I say point to my animal and say זו חטאת
zo chatat and it can be used by someone else?
And it could be what?
It could be used by someone else who does have an obligation.
Yeah, so that's a question because you know is there such a
sense of like a generic חטאת? chatat? I mean a חטאת chatat
is supposed to be brought specifically for a חטא. chet. So what
is there exactly the status if it's not specifically for a חטא?
chet? So even תוספות Tosafot who argues on רש״י Rashi says one
minute,
yeah, says that the גמרא Gemara in נדרים Nedarim says that the
status of saying it when you're not obligated is that it's לא
קדוש lo kadosh at all. So a חטאת chatat really requires the
context of a sin, right? It really is coming almost as a
consequence of the sin, in the context of having sinned. So to
make a חטאת chatat generically is a meaningless statement. So it's actually
quite fascinating. If you said הרי זו חטאת harei zo chatat and
you're not obligated in a sin, then it's not like oh you
redeem it and whatever I might have said before that was a
mistake. Anyway, it's not like you redeem it and you hold on
and you wait for it. It's not meaningful unless it's coming after
a sin and in that context.
And if I say a חטאת chatat for when I do sin?
No, you cannot. Right.
And if I
say
זו חטאת zo chatat nothing happens, if I say זו תמורת חטאת
zo tmurat chatat it has to die?
No, not חטאת. chatat. Oh, that's why תוספות Tosafot argues on רש״י.
Rashi. Okay. So תוספות Tosafot says only if you say זו תמורת
חטאת. zo tmurat chatat. Yeah. Okay.
So if I say זו תמורת חטאת zo tmurat chatat and you
have no חטאת chatat to begin with, you can't say it's meaningless?
Right. תמורה tmura only works if you have the original thing in
front of you. Okay, so if you must have a חטאת chatat
in front of you that was coming as a result of sin
and then you said זו תמורת חטאת. zo tmurat chatat.
Okay, so if I say זו חטאת zo chatat or תמורת חטאת
tmurat chatat and I have not sinned and I have no חטאת
chatat then
it's meaningless.
Right. And he uses חולין? chulin?
Yeah. I mean רש״י Rashi says for some reason it's תמות, tamut,
but תוספות Tosafot says it's again,
but no one's going to say I want at least קדושת דמים,
kedushat damim, no it's completely meaningless. Yeah. Okay. I don't know if
anybody would say that it's something like you know תימכר לצורכי חטאת
timacher letzorchei chatat because since you used those words, but we don't
say that here generally because there was actually you know there was
Right. And he uses the חולין Chulin hands. Yeah. And רש"י Rashi
says for some reason it's חולין. Chulin. But תוספות Tosafot says it's
תמורה. Temurah. But now I'm going to say I want it at
least has קדושת דמים. Kedushat Damim. No, it's completely meaningless. Yeah. Okay.
I don't know if anybody would say that it's something like כמכר
לצרכי חטאת Ke-mecher Le-tzorchei Chatat because since you use those words, although
we don't say that here generally because there was actually there was
really no קדושה. Kedushah. It's not like your car cases. Right, exactly.
Okay. So let's see. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this:
Okay. So תוספות Tosafot which is the גירסא Girsa of תמורה. Temurah.
He says it based on the תוספתא. Tosefta. So okay, ושוין, Ve-shavin,
they agree, באומר חצי חטאת וחצי עולה, Be-omer Chatzi Chatat Ve-chatzi Olah,
שתמות, She-tamut, that if you say half חטאת Chatat first, not half
עולה olah, first, half חטאת Chatat first, that it does die. Because
again, according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, the first thing you says
is what takes effect first. And once you say half חטאת, Chatat,
the whole thing becomes a חטאת, Chatat, or according to the תמורת
חטאת. Tmurat Chatat. Okay. שוין מני? Shavin Mani? So who agrees? רבי
מאיר? Rabbi Meir? או רב יצחק סבר רבי מאיר? O Rav Yitzchak
Savar Rabbi Meir? פשיטא, Pshita, of course he agrees. He always says
you do the first thing. So if you first said half חטאת,
Chatat, that takes effect first and it's a חטאת Chatat or a
תמורת חטאת. Tmurat Chatat. So no, מהו דתימא, Mah De-teima, אי לאו
דאשמעינן, Ei Lav De-ashmeinan, had you not said explicitly that רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir agrees in this case, הוה אמינא, Hava Amina, טעמא דרבי
מאיר לאו משום תפוס לשון ראשון. Taama De-rabbi Meir Lav Mishum Tfos
Lashon Rishon. Maybe רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is not based on doing
the first thing, on the, on that the first words out of
your mouth take effect. אלא היינו טעמא, Ela Hainu Taama, and this
is his reasoning,
דחטאת מעורבת קריבה, De-chatat Meurevet Kreiva, that maybe he really feels that
it's fifty-fifty. If it is fifty-fifty, so then why can you bring
it? Because maybe he has a position that as long as it's
not a hundred percent of a תמורת חטאת, Tmurat Chatat, as long
as it's only a fifty percent of a תמורת חטאת, Tmurat Chatat,
maybe that's not enough to say תמות. Tamut. I'm reading it תוספות'ס
Tosafot's way that it's about תמורה. Temurah. Maybe that's not enough to
say תמות. Tamut. Maybe in order to say תמות Tamut it has
to be a hundred percent of a תמורת חטאת. Tmurat Chatat. ואפילו
כי אמר חצי חטאת ואחר כך אמר חצי עולה קריבה, Ve-afilu Ki
Amar Chatzi Chatat Ve-achar Kach Amar Chatzi Olah Kreiva, and maybe even
if he said fifty-fifty it would work. Maybe actually he says the
whole thing takes effect, you don't go sequentially, and maybe the reason
he said before it worked is he said that half of a
תמורת חטאת Tmurat Chatat is not enough to say that it has
to die. So therefore in the reverse case it would also be
half and half and you could bring it. קא משמע לן דלא,
Ka Mashma Lan De-lo, it's telling you no, it's not that he
says the whole thing takes effect, he says only the first half,
and when you say first חצי חטאת, Chatzi Chatat, that takes effect
and the whole thing becomes a חטאת. Chatat. Now of course it's
a little bizarre, how would I thought that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says the whole thing takes effect? What about everything we've been learning
up until now where he says תפוס לשון ראשון? Tfos Lashon Rishon?
But this is I think along the lines of the first statement
we began with today, that maybe to nuance רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
a little bit. Maybe if you phrase it in a very indicative
way that shows you mean all together, we would say it means
all together. So when you say half and half, if anything might
indicate I mean not sequential but as one unit, when I say
half and half that really sounds like it. Okay, so that's what
the גמרא Gemara is now saying. Maybe I would have said here
maybe רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir agrees you don't apply it sequentially, you
said half and half you apply it all as a package. Why
do I bring it? Because maybe even half of a תמורת חטאת
Tmurat Chatat can be brought. So this is telling me no, that's
not what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says. Even when you say half
and half, it's תפוס לשון ראשון, Tfos Lashon Rishon, it takes effect
sequentially, and if the first thing you said was חצי חטאת, Chatzi
Chatat, it all becomes a חטאת Chatat and you deal with it
appropriately, and if it's a תמורת חטאת, Tmurat Chatat, it all has
to die.
The only time he agrees is when either it can be half
is when you say this and only if, you know, if you're
very explicit.
Let this happen only if that happens. Or according to, that's fine,
but according to what is less to be expected at least according
to the statement of רב יצחק Rav Yitzchak at the beginning, if
you said תמורת עולה ושלמים, Tmurat Olah Ve-shlamim, you didn't add the
extra word תמורה, Tmurah, then he might agree. But that's against the
real thrust. The thrust is is that regardless of phrasing, unless you're
a hundred percent explicit, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir always says the first
thing to take effect sequentially. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara goes
on.
תניא אידך, Tanya Idach, we taught another ברייתא. Braita. אמר בהמה זו
חצי עולה וחצי שלמים, Amar Behema Zu Chatzi Olah Ve-chatzi Shlamim, okay,
so there you go again Michael, not a תמורה Temurah case. You
said half עולה Olah half שלמים. shelamim.
Did תוספות Tosafot say it's also תמורה?
Temurah? No. קדושה Kedusha because this is clearly not. The only reason
he said before was of
תמות. Tamut. קדושה ואינה קריבה, Kedusha Ve-eina Kreiva, it's holy but you
can't bring it as a קרבן Korban because this is according to
not רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir but רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, it's a
half and a half. So what's half and a half? So half
and a half, you don't bring an עולה שלמים Olah Shlamim as
a קרבן. Korban. Well, not it's nothing, it's a half and a
half, you don't bring, but you don't bring an עולה Olah שלמים
Shlamim. as a קרבן. Korban. It has to be one or the
other.
עושה תמורה, Osa Tmurah, now let's say you said after you did
your half and half, you had your little hybrid, you took another
animal and you said זאת תמורת זו. Zot Tmurat Zo. Okay, so
your next animal is also a half-half. ותמורתו כיוצא בו, U-tmurato Ke-yotzei
Bo, and your new animal is just like it, it's a half
and a half, okay, it's a hybrid.
But you can't make a תמורה Tmurah on that one though because,
well, as it's
right, but that's a different הלכה. Halacha. Now מני, Mani, who is
this going by? רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, it's רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
because he says that it starts off as half and half. So
פשיטא, Pshita, of course it's רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. So
פשיטא דקדושה ואינה קריבה, Pshita De-kdusha Ve-eina Kreiva, of course you can't
bring it as a קרבן, Korban, it's half and half, and of
course we know you can't bring such a thing as a קרבן.
Korban. No, תמורתה אצטריכא ליה, Tmurata Itztricha Lei, I need to tell
me the הלכה Halacha that the תמורה Tmurah follows the same status.
Why? דמהו דתימא, De-mahu De-teima, נהי דהא לא קרבה, Nehi De-ha Lo
Karva, תמורתה תקרב, Tmurata Tikrav, maybe you can't bring it, but maybe
I should be able to bring the תמורה, Tmurah, קא משמע לן,
Ka Mashma Lan, it tells you you can't. Why can't you? מאי
שנא היא דלא קרבה, Mai Shna Hi De-lo Karva, why can't you
bring the original one? דהויא לה קדושה דחויה, De-hava Lah Kedusha De-chuya,
because it's a pushed off קדושה, Kedusha, it's a קדושה Kedusha that
can't be
used, קדושה, kedusha, so it as well cannot be brought. תוספות tosafot
says, תוספות tosafot says, what's the חידוש? chiddush? If it's a half
and a half, the תמורה tmura is a half and a half.
Of course! So תוספות tosafot says no, actually what I would have
thought was when you say let this be an exchange תמורה, tmura,
you're trying, you're trying to improve the situation. Now, meaning obviously you're
not going to remove it from the original one even if maybe
you think you are, but at least if you're bringing, if you're
trying to do something now, you're trying to make it better. So
when you say this is an exchange, what you're maybe in your
mind what you really mean is let it have one of the
קדושות. kedushot. Let it have the שלמים shlamim part of that original
animal, or let it have the עולה ola part of that original
animal. And therefore maybe it works, maybe this תמורה tmura is all
a שלמים shlamim or all an עולה ola depending on what you
were thinking. And the answer of קמשמע לן, kamashma lan, this is
the way תוספות tosafot reads it, is not that we don't say
you were thinking that. We say you were thinking it's half and
half. Then it wouldn't be so interesting. The answer is even if
you were thinking that, but since it originates in an animal that
can't be brought, even if now you gave it a קדושה kedusha
of just the שלמים shlamim part, but it was from a קדושה
kedusha that couldn't be brought. So this too is also can't be
brought even if it's only קדושת שלמים. kedushat shlamim. So the נפקא
מינה nafka mina according to תוספות tosafot is that when you let
the תמורה tmura graze and then you redeem it, all of that
money, the money would not be split half and half. All of
the money of the תמורה tmura would go either all to an
עולה ola or all to a שלמים. shlamim. Which one? Depending on
which you had in mind. But according to תוספות tosafot it's a
bigger חידוש chiddush that even if you're trying to hone in on
just half of it, but it doesn't matter because the nature of
the קדושה kedusha now is not usable קדושה. kedusha. So even if
you don't transfer both statuses, even only one, it still cannot be
brought.
So the original one is 50/50, meaning
you split the money. But the תמורה tmura is 100%.
Right, that's the way תוספות tosafot
reads it.
100% תמורה.
tmura. 100% no, 100% עולה ola or 100% שלמים shlamim depending on
which one you were thinking. At least that's but it can't be
brought because that's because it's called קדושה דחויה. kedusha dichuya.
But let's say you actually said I want this animal to be
תמורה tmura of the שלמים shlamim part.
Let's say you actually explicitly said it.
Probably, because that's what we were thinking.
Yes, even if you said, right, even if you said, according to
תוספות tosafot it won't help because the origin is קדושה דחויה. kedusha
dichuya. Okay. Now again, it's a little different because if the original
animal was a בעל מום, ba'al mum, right, then the second animal,
well actually that's not true, the גמרא gemara actually has that מחלוקת
machloket if you remember way, way back about two weeks ago, right,
what happens if you do a תמורה tmura of a תמים tamim
for a בעל מום? ba'al mum? And actually there too, except according
to one תנא, tana, the גמרא gemara was inclined to say that
the תמורה tmura couldn't be brought as well since the origin was
a בעל מום. ba'al mum. So certainly in this case, this case
is even worse than a בעל מום. ba'al mum. בעל מום ba'al
mum had קדושה kedusha that originally could be brought and then it
got a מום. mum. This one at the very outset was this
weird hybrid that could never be brought. Okay, so now the גמרא
gemara goes on. אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Yochanan, בהמה של שני
שותפין. behema shel shnei shutfin. Now let's say you have an animal
that's owned by partners.
והקדיש חציה שלו. v'hikdish chetzya shelo. So you were מקדיש makdish the
half that was yours. Okay, now here, even if normally when you
say, right, until now we've been assuming if you're מקדיש makdish half
the whole animal becomes קדוש kadosh because that is a what do
you because that's you know the principle that certainly if you're מקדיש
makdish a part that the life depends on, some say any part,
the whole animal becomes קדוש. kadosh. But it can't happen if only
half is yours because you're not in a position to define the
other half of the animal. You don't own the other half. So
in that case, you that would be a scenario where you really
could sanctify just half of
it. Okay, וחזר ולקח חציה אחרת. v'chazar v'lakach chetzya acheret. You went
and you bought the other half. Now you might think that as
soon as you buy the other half, the קדושה kedusha automatically spreads,
right, because it
was trying to define the whole thing, was held back because you
didn't own it. As soon as now you own it, maybe it
defines the whole status of the whole thing. But this assumes not
that way. This assumes that if it didn't happen at the time
of sanctification, then it remains only half קדוש. kadosh. So you could
actually get a status of half קדוש. kadosh. One minute.
Now you own the whole thing, והקדישה, v'hikdisha, and now you sanctify
the other half. Okay, now you're in a position to sanctify the
whole thing. Okay, so maybe now, first it was a half עולה,
ola, now you made it a full עולה. ola. You sanctified the
other half. Maybe now I can bring it as an עולה. ola.
So it says קדושה ואינה קריבה. kedusha v'eina kreva. It's קדוש kadosh
but it cannot be brought. Why? Because it already was נדחה. nidche.
Meaning at the point it was already half קדוש, kadosh, it was
already in a status of not able to be brought. So something
that was קדוש kadosh that couldn't be brought, that has a sense
of דיחוי, dichuy, pushed away, sort of stigmatized, labeled as not usable.
And now even though you've given it a full קדושה, kedusha, you
cannot change its status back into being usable. קדושה ואינה קריבה, kedusha
v'eina kreva, ועושה תמורה, v'osa tmura, you can make a תמורה, tmura,
ותמורתה כיוצא בה. u'tmurata k'yotzei ba. The תמורה tmura is like it.
And this is even better like along the lines of תוספות's tosafot
last case. Even though the תמורה tmura now is a full עולה,
ola, but it's an unusable עולה ola because this one has a
status, it wasn't a hybrid, it was a full עולה, ola, but
it was a full עולה ola that already at its original stage
was נדחה, nidche, and therefore is an unusable עולה. ola. And therefore
the תמורה tmura as well becomes an עולה ola but an unusable
עולה. ola. Okay, כיוצא בה. kayotzei vah. Now before I read the
next line, Charlie had a question because next line,
wouldn't there be another issue that you've consecrated, by consecrating half of
the animal, you've now prevented the owner of the other half from
benefiting from the animal. Would there be a potential...
Oh, you mean like it wouldn't be fair to him because you're
subverting his... Exactly. Yeah, so there's actually an interesting question about that,
meaning, you know, that comes up in a couple of places where
based on the way you can sort of sanctify certain things, you
can indirectly subvert another person's rights. Like if you had a lien
on my property and I sanctified it, so then you weren't able
to exercise your lien and cases like that where the גמרא Gemara
deals with questions about whether I have to compensate you because I
cause indirectly caused you loss. But that doesn't the fact the question
about the consequence and compensation doesn't actually as long as right now
I am not directly sort of, you know, as long as now
I'm within my rights, I'm only doing something to my property. You
know, it's like the old joke, right? The guys are in the
middle of a boat, you know, of a lifeboat in the middle
in the river, the guy's making a hole and he's in his
side, says what does it bother you? I'm doing it on my
half. Right? But actually, right, they use that example to speak about
the concept of ערבות arivus and right, responsibility. Anyway, but the point
is is that halachically yes, since I'm doing something within my property
rights, even though you wind up being constrained and limited, the only
question is whether I have to compensate you, not whether I'm able
to do it. Okay, did you have a question? Okay, fine.
So that's yes, yeah, I do, but this this is only a
problem it frames it as if once you're מקדיש makdish the rest
of it, but what if I didn't do it?
That's what I said. I said you could have argued that even
if you're not מקדיש makdish it happens automatically, but that, you know,
that just the nature of a חלות קדושה chalut kedusha is waiting,
is sort of prone to define the whole animal, but it just
has the ownership standing in the way. So you could have said
that. But no, I'm saying right, but the גמרא Gemara doesn't. Right,
maybe it's maybe it's making a חידוש chiddush that even if you
were מקדיש makdish it that that would certainly be no good because
that's originating from the original bad קדושה. kedusha. So even if you're
מקדיש makdish it, it doesn't improve it. But the simple sense of
the גמרא Gemara implies that no, that if at the moment of
הקדשה hakdasha you were not able it didn't define the whole thing,
it does not define it later even if you remove the obstacle.
Okay, so it would remain half קדוש. kadosh.
So it would remain half קדוש kadosh and you would have to
wait till it gets a מום mum and then you redeem it.
Exactly. Okay, even now you wait till it gets a מום. mum.
Okay, so wouldn't it be like it's still it would be the
same thing, it's still קדושה ואינה קריבה kedusha ve'eina kreiva and it's
a תמורה. tmura.
Yeah, but the חידוש chiddush is even if you're מקדיש makdish the
second half. Now I'm in a position to מקדיש makdish the whole
thing and you might think now that I can improve the situation,
but no, it's still defined by the pushed off קדושה kedusha originally.
Okay, and that's what now we get to this famous line that
the גמרא Gemara has a number of times according to רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan and it almost always accompanies the י"ג תוספות Yud Gimmel
Tosafot and I'll tell you why in a minute. Okay, שמע מינה
תלת. shma mina tlat. We learn from this three things. This is
a very common שמע מינה תלת shma mina tlat that the גמרא
Gemara has, this particular גמרא Gemara often says שמע מינה תלת, shma
mina tlat, we learn three things after a statement is made, but
this is a very common sort of common one that repeats, you
can look on the side, it's quoted a lot of places. Here
are the three things we learn from this statement. שמע מינה קדושת
דמים נדחה. shma mina kedushat damim nidcha. We see that even though
it only has a קדושה kedusha of value, it still creates דיחוי.
dichuy. Meaning, when you originally sanctified it, it was not in a
position to be brought as a קרבן, korban, right? It was only
as a position because you only owned half of it. So you
might say the concept of דיחוי dichuy being pushed off means, right,
for example, let me give you a simple example, something was never
a קרבן. korban. I have an animal that got a מום mum
and then the מום mum went away or something like that. Okay,
I wouldn't say oh, it's נדחה, nidcha, because if the first time
I sanctify it it's fine, who cares about its past history? The
past history only labels it once it gets into the world of
קדושה. kedusha. So I might have thought that if when I originally
sanctify it it's never yet fit to be a קרבן, korban, I
only half own it, it's even though it's a קדושה kedusha only
for its future value to be used but never the thing itself
has never in a position to be used, maybe it can't yet
get a status of being נדחה, nidcha, being pushed off because it's
not even relevant yet for that category. No, even so, even if
it's only קדושת דמים, kedushat damim, it could still be labeled as
pushed off, נדחה. nidcha. ושמע מינה, v'shma mina, you also see בעלי
חיים נדחין, ba'alei chayim nidchin, that even though it's alive it can
be pushed off. There's a major debate of whether you have a
דיחוי dichuy by live animals, that it might only be that once
something's already dead and you're dealing with like I don't know the
blood or the meat or something like that, that then, you know,
when something is purely an object and it's not yet live which
has a sense of sort of of dynamism and and change and
so on, you know, when it's purely objectified then it has a
label that sticks to it. But as soon as something is alive,
you know, that can allow for this greater concept of change and
it's not permanent and it's not static and therefore its label does
not necessarily, you know, adhere. So do we say בעלי חיים נדחין,
ba'alei chayim nidchin, can something be considered pushed off even if it's
alive? And here, so that's a major debate, but here yes, because
the thing is... alive, that's the second thing we learned from it.
And שמע מינה דחויי מעיקרא הוי דחויי. shma mina dichuy mei'ikara havei
dichuy. A third thing which is also majorly debated is maybe things
only get a status of נדחה nidcheh if they were first fit
and then they were pushed off. They were first in the category
and then they were like rejected. But if they were sort of
rejected from the get-go, that's not as much of a stigma. The
example I sort of give is, you know, if like somebody is
let's say applying to the ישיבה yeshiva and we say, you know,
you know, like we sort of say maybe you want to come
back and apply a year from now, you know, after you've addressed
certain things, dot dot dot dot dot. Then you look at their
application, you're willing to consider them a second time. But if they're
actually already in and then you ask them to leave,
you're not as willing to look at them a second time. So
once something is actually fit and then it says, oh, you were
actually fit and now you're stamped as unacceptable, it remains unacceptable. If
something never got into being fit at the beginning and the first
time we look at it, then maybe we'll be prepared to look
at it, you know, even if that problem is solved. Now, the
reason, so those are the three things because here even from the
get-go it wasn't acceptable and nevertheless it retains that status of דחוי
dichuy of being pushed off. Now the reason we have a huge
תוספות Tosafot here, we almost have it every time we have this
threesome, is first of all just tries to make it work with
other statements of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan but a major part is
that he says the first and the third are the exact same
thing if you were paying attention. Because דחוי מעיקרא, dichuy mei'ikara, if
something is דחוי מעיקרא dichuy mei'ikara is considered דחוי, dichuy, well to
be דחוי מעיקרא dichuy mei'ikara if you're pushed off from the beginning,
it means you never had קדושת הגוף. kedushat haguf. You only had
קדושת דמים. kedushat damim. The only way you get קדושת הגוף kedushat
haguf is if first you were completely fit, you got the קדושה
kedusha and then a problem arose.
Okay, so every case of נראה ונדחה, nireh venidcheh, first being fit
and then being pushed off, is a case where it had קדושת
הגוף. kedushat haguf. Every case of דחוי מעיקרא, dichuy mei'ikara, if from
the very beginning you weren't fit, so then the קדושה kedusha never
became a קדושת הגוף, kedushat haguf, it was only קדושת דמים. kedushat
damim. So why is this listed as three things? It's really two.
So תוספות Tosafot tries to find scenarios where you could have one
without having the other. You could have a case where it has
only קדושת דמים kedushat damim with being always fit or you could
have to be fit with only with anyway he tries to have
cases only one the other but probably the easier answer is, although
I don't know if it's really fully sufficient, is that the גמרא
Gemara never does a שמע מינה תרי. shma mina terei. The גמרא
Gemara only does a שמע מינה תלת. shma mina tlat. You know,
it's like they tell you in when you're learning about like speech
class or whatever, you know, always do things in threes. People think
in threes. Oh yeah, they say people always think in threes. So
there are three lessons we can learn from this. Never two, never
four. Three lessons. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara never has a שמע
מינה shma mina four, never has a שמע מינה תרי, shma mina
terei, it only has a שמע מינה תלת. shma mina tlat. So
the fact that one and three are basically the same, even though
they tell you different things conceptually, I mean although they're somewhat similar,
but one is that even though the קדושה kedusha is only קדושת
דמים kedushat damim and the other is that even though the animal
was sort of not even yet in the category, although those of
course are related or pretty much the same, even if they always
99% of the time describe the same scenario, it allows you to
say three things. But תוספות Tosafot does try to find scenarios where
they will not be the same. Let me just tell you what
one or two of them was.
Okay, so one he has for example, the גמרא Gemara included in
the idea of דחוי, dichuy, speaks about if the problem is not
in the animal but the problem is in the person. So you
could have a type of a person that's not in a position
to bring a קרבן. korban. Like if a person basically, you know,
a מומר, mumar, a person basically, you know, decided, you know, sort
of rebelled and said I'm not keeping anything, I reject the entire
system, or maybe even rejected let's say he sinned about a particular
sin, about שבת, Shabbat, and but he didn't just happen to sin
about שבת, Shabbat, he completely decided he's rejecting שמירת שבת. shmirat Shabbat.
So that type of a person can't bring a קרבן. korban. You
can't bring a קרבן korban if you are basically in a status
that you have completely rejected the system. Okay, so if you're like
say let's say that type of a person and you sanctify, so
on the one hand it's דחוי מעיקרא dichuy mei'ikara because from the
very get-go you're not fit to bring a קרבן, korban, but it's
still a קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf because the problem isn't in the
animal, the problem is in you. So the animal could still have
a קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf even though it's a scenario of דחוי
מעיקרא. dichuy mei'ikara.
So what do you do? So it would also be according well
if you פסקן pasken that it's that these things can be דחוי,
dichuy, it would be a problem. But if you say אין דחוי
ein dichuy but you know that depends on how you פסקן, pasken,
but according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan it would be דחוי. dichuy.
You wait until he does תשובה teshuva and the whole thing. Okay,
so anyway, alright, so you have those three things but almost always
one and three are the same although תוספות Tosafot gives scenarios. So
what according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says why does it get
rejected? It gets rejected because it can't be used. Once it can't
be used it retains that label that's called the concept of דחוי.
dichuy. It applies even though the animal from the get-go wasn't usable,
דחוי מעיקרא dichuy mei'ikara was never usable, which also means the קדושה
kedusha was only קדושת דמים, kedushat damim, so קדושת דמים kedushat damim
is נדחה, nidcheh, it was not a קדושת הגוף. kedushat haguf. Those
two are essentially the same. And
even though it was
sort of... That's if you're מקדיש makdish it for בדק הבית, bedek
habayit, but קדושת דמים kedushat damim does not mean
בדק הבית. bedek habayit. קדושת דמים לעולה, kedushat damim le'olah, קדושת דמים
לחטאת kedushat damim lechatat or whatever. Okay, it's money to be used
towards a particular קרבן. korban. It is not a קדושת בדק הבית
kedushat bedek habayit which is basically just owned by the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. But in the מומר mumar case we don't say that
since he right just can't bring
it therefore correct.
If it's something you're מקדיש makdish as a קרבן, korban, its only
identity is as a קרבן. korban. It's not just generic right because
as I've said for a long time the difference is that by
בדק הבית bedek habayit you're basically it's basically a transfer of property.
By קרבן korban it's basically a change of the identity of the
animal.
But you can still מקדיש makdish it though for בדק הבית bedek
habayit even if he's a מומר? mumar?
Yeah, oh sure, we accept donations from everyone.
I was going to say non-Jews can contribute animals
for yeah non-Jews can
bring עולות. olos. They can bring קרבנות, korbanos, yeah. Okay, אמר אביי.
Amar Abaye. הכל מודים, Hakol modim, everybody agrees, היכא דאמר heicha de'amar
חצי עולה וחצי מעשר, chatzi olah vechatzi maaser, דברי הכל עולה divrei
hakol olah
וקרבה עולה. vekreiva olah.
So if you say half עולה olah and half מעשר, maaser, everybody
says it's an עולה olah and you can bring it. Why? Why
isn't it half and half and then you can't bring a hybrid
animal according to רבי יוסי? Rabbi Yossi? So רש"י Rashi says oh
because when you say half מעשר maaser it's meaningless because you're not
actually in the process of making doing מעשר. maaser. So it's a
meaningless statement. So therefore only your עולה olah statement takes effect. Okay,
תוספות Tosafot says that would be a little bit too obvious and
also it's not going to fit with the continuation of the גמרא.
Gemara. So תוספות Tosafot actually has two other possibilities. One is he
actually said תמורת מעשר, tmuras maaser, okay, or the other is actually
you did say מעשר maaser but you said it as your animal
you were counting your מעשר maaser animals. And as the tenth one
came out you say when this tenth one comes down I'm going
to call it מעשר, maaser, I want it actually to be half
and half. Okay, now if all of that is true according to
תוספות Tosafot
does that mean you get out of מעשר? maaser?
So according right so according to רש"י Rashi you understand why the
מעשר maaser half part doesn't take effect because it was a meaningless
statement. You can't do מעשר maaser when you're not counting. According to
תוספות Tosafot why doesn't it take effect? So תוספות Tosafot says let
me just check תוספות Tosafot again.
Yeah, so תוספות Tosafot says although this is somewhat against not against
but somewhat in contrast to
the גמרא Gemara before that said if it's between you and a
natural קדושה kedushah like בכור, bechor, right, you go by the natural
קדושה kedushah not what you're trying to do. But here he says
מעשר maaser is not natural. מעשר maaser requires your act of counting.
So since מעשר maaser requires a greater effort to designate it and
define it and any another type of sanctification like עולה olah comes
only through your verbal act, that is has more dominance than the
מעשר maaser act. Okay, so that's how תוספות Tosafot understands. You tried
to do a hybrid both as you're counting מעשר, maaser, your verbal
act is more powerful because the מעשר maaser requires you know more
effort to designate something as מעשר. maaser.
So you can get out of מעשר maaser every time by doing
this?
Well, you can always get out of מעשר maaser by it's an
interesting question whether no probably you would have to then the next
one would have to be your מעשר maaser because if you actually
have a sanctified animal in your flock you know it doesn't count
towards the ten, right? So you know so it shouldn't have been
part of the ten that were counted although here it was sort
of it was not sanctified before it was counted it was sanctified
as it was counted so that's an interesting question.
But you can just say forget the מעשר maaser part. I'm just
going one two three four five six seven eight nine עולה, olah,
one two three four five six seven eight nine חטאת.
chatas. Right, but again well possibly yes but then again as I
said that might mean that eleven now has to become ten because
now you've excluded that from the group. Okay, so anyway so that's
that. So that's the way תוספות Tosafot reads it. רש"י Rashi reads
it that the words מעשר maaser were meaningless because you weren't counting
it.
So basically it's not a מחלוקת machlokes in terms of concept just
a מחלוקת machlokes how to explain this. Meaning רש"י Rashi would agree
with תוספות Tosafot that if you were counting it would be the
same thing?
No, not clear that רש"י. Rashi. תוספות Tosafot is מחדש mechadesh a
new idea that even if you're counting the עולה olah takes precedence
because it's a more powerful
קדושה. kedushah. Okay, היכא דאמר Heicha de'amar חצי תמורה וחצי מעשר. chatzi
tmura vechatzi maaser. Now let's say you said half תמורה tmura half
מעשר. maaser. מאי? Mai? Which one wins? תמורה קרבה Tmura kreiva שכן
נוהגת בכל הקדשים. sheken noheges bechol hakodashim. Is תמורה tmura the more
powerful words because it applies to all sacrifices all animals
you know because it applies because it applies to all קרבנות korbanos
whereas מעשר maaser only applies to you know every tenth animal and
so on. It's a more limited
קדושה. kedushah. או דלמא O dilma מעשר קרבה maaser kreiva שכן מקדיש
לפניו ולאחריו. sheken makdish lefanav ule'acharav. מעשר Maaser is a powerful קדושה
kedushah because if you remember if you call nine מעשר maaser and
eleven מעשר maaser it also works. So מעשר maaser has a certain
power. So which one dominates? More so it says תיקו. teiku. Now
again the question is what does this mean? I mean according to
רש"י Rashi this is why תוספות Tosafot rejects רש"י. Rashi. If your
words מעשר maaser are meaningless when you're not counting how can you
ask which one words wins out? So תוספות Tosafot says oh so
רש"י Rashi says oh well תמורה tmura is also meaningless. Why is
the words תמורה tmura meaningless? Because I don't have a תמורה. tmura.
Because it's a scenario exactly that there was no קרבן korban in
front of you. So you have two meaningless statements which one wins
out? תוספות Tosfos says, two meaningless statements which one wins out? Neither
win out, they're both meaningless. So that's why תוספות, Tosfos, that's why
תוספות Tosfos rejects רש"י, Rashi, and therefore תוספות Tosfos says, no, you
actually are doing the תמורה tmurah versus a מעשר, ma'aser, and the
question here is that both of them, as opposed to עולה, olah,
which is more powerful than מעשר ma'aser because it works just by
your word, תמורה tmurah also is a little bit dependent. תמורה tmurah
requires that there be an animal in front of you. מעשר ma'aser
requires that you're counting an animal. So in this type of a
case, you know, where both of them are somewhat of equal weight,
they want to know the weightier one, which one went out, but
how do we define the weightier one? Now I should say that
this last line of the גמרא Gemara is a little strange, because
this last line of the גמרא, Gemara, you know, you would have
thought that according to רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, it's not there's no
question of went out. You're trying to do both and both take
effect. But again, the difference here is that you did not say,
well,
yeah, actually it is a problem, because you actually said half and
half. So particularly if you said half and half, you actually would
think that why don't both, why doesn't it exactly take effect as
you would? Why is it that one of them more dominates and
takes precedence over the other? So that whole idea that רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosi would agree that there's a case where if you had
a more powerful one it could win out, why don't you say
if you say עולה olah and שלמים, shlamim, עולה olah is a
more powerful קדושה kedusha than שלמים? shlamim? So the whole concept here
that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi would agree is a little strange, and
the גמרא Gemara is limiting it to these cases of if you
would, these weaker קדושות. kedushas. If they were both let's say equal
strong קדושות, kedushas, classical, a classic שלמים shlamim or whatever, we wouldn't
say it. But מעשר ma'aser and תמורה, tmurah, which both of which
are a little dependent on other circumstances, that's what תוספות Tosfos says,
maybe one of them will sort of go by the wayside and
the other one will dominate. Okay, now we go on to the
next משנה. mishna. Let's take a look. הרי זו תחת זו. Harei
zo tachas zo. Now we are finally at the end of twenty-six
דף daf after we've sort of paid our dues, we are getting
to find out how you actually do the act of תמורה. tmurah.
Okay, so if you say הרי זו תחת זו, harei zo tachas
zo, תמורה זו, tmurah zo, חליפה זו, chalifa zo, animal B is
under, instead of A, תמורה tmurah in exchange of A, right, חליפה
זו
chalifa
zo in exchange for A, all of these words are תמורה tmurah
words, they're an attempt to exchange. הרי זו תמורה, Harei zo tmurah,
it's a תמורה. tmurah. Now if you say זו מחוללת על זו,
zo mechuleles al zo, this one should be redeemed on the other,
like that's what you do with an animal with a מום. mum.
You remove the קדושה kedusha and you put it on money or
you put it on another animal, and that's what you're supposed to
do when an animal gets a מום. mum. So if you say,
now at first we're assuming that the animal doesn't have a blemish,
but nevertheless you use the words of redemption, it is redeemed on
this, אין זו תמורה, ein zo tmurah, it's not a תמורה. tmurah.
And if the animal doesn't have a מום, mum, it's a meaningless
statement, you didn't transgress, nothing became קדוש, kadosh, it was just a
meaningless statement. ואם היה הקדש בעל מום, Ve'im haya hekdesh ba'al mum,
and if however הקדש hekdesh actually the sanctified one had a blemish,
יוצא לחולין וצריך לעשות דמים, yotzei l'chulin v'tzarich la'asos damim, then actually
it works. The first animal gets de-sanctified because you redeemed it. Now
what does צריך לעשות דמים tzarich la'asos damim mean is you have
to assess the value, and we'll talk about that tomorrow, meaning that
if the second animal was not of as much value as the
first, then you have to make up the difference because you're redeeming
it, it has to be of equivalent value. We'll talk in detail
about what that means tomorrow, but it means since it was a
redemption, you should make sure that the second one was of equal
value to the first. So let's take a look now at the
גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara now gets into the issue of the
terminology. But I will just say again conceptually, the interesting thing is
that the גמרא Gemara never exactly explains conceptually, it hints to as
we'll see conceptually how they're different, but never fully articulates the difference
of תמורה tmurah and מחולל. mechulal. Now you would have said naturally
that oh, well if it has a blemish then you're redeeming it.
But of course the גמרא Gemara said earlier no, that part of
the prohibition of תמורה, tmurah, רע בטוב וטוב ברע, ra b'tov v'tov
b'ra, is even if the original one has a blemish, you can
do תמורה tmurah even if you're trying to exchange it with an
unblemished one. Well then what makes that the prohibited act of תמורה
tmurah as opposed to the acceptable and appropriate act of פדיון pidyon
and being מחלל mechallel and being redeeming it? So it seems that
conceptually the difference is that which animal am I starting from? The
גמרא Gemara tomorrow will talk about which animal, well I referenced it
before, which animal am I putting my hand on almost? If what
I'm trying to do is remove the קדושה kedusha from this because
this has a מום mum and I'm removing the קדושה, kedusha, now
I'm placing it on something else, that's acceptable. That's called redeeming, I'm
taking the קדושה kedusha away from that. If however I'm leaving the
קדושה kedusha there and I'm saying I want and I'm focusing on
this, I want this to take that instead, and I haven't started
by removing the קדושה, kedusha, then that is תמורה. tmurah. Now why
is that such a worse thing? It's not exactly clear, meaning there's
two questions to ask. One is like why is it a prohibition?
And the other question to ask is why does it make the
second animal קדוש? kadosh? The second animal The second question is easier
to answer. Because if I start with the second animal and I
leave that without addressing its קדושה, kedusha, I am accepting its קדושה
kedusha to stay and I'm bringing this into sort of the ambit
of the other one, then it gets, you know, seized by that
קדושה, kedusha, right? If I start by removing this קדושה, kedusha, then
fine, I've started by taking the קדושה kedusha away. But if I
have that קדושה kedusha there and I'm saying and this one should
be in its stead, I'm bringing this if you would into the
environment of the other one, then it also gets the קדושה kedusha
before it's able, you know, and it's not able to remove the
קדושה. kedusha. So conceptually why the second one becomes קדוש kadosh if
I start with the second one makes sense because I haven't yet
changed the קדושה kedusha of the first one. But why is it
prohibited, you know, is not exactly as clear, unless again it's something
along the same lines, that if I actually am removing the קדושה
kedusha and I should be because it has a מום, mum, fine,
that's acceptable, that's what I should do. But if I am sort
of accepting it with its קדושה kedusha status, I have yet to
remove it, right, and I'm trying to have something take its stead,
so I'm trying to take this non-sanctified animal and challenging one as
it were that still has its קדושה, kedusha, undermining one that still
has its קדושה, kedusha, that is seen as like inappropriate. So if
you want to use my example before about like a student or
whatever, like by employment, okay, you first want to give somebody notice
that they're fired before you start interviewing for the next job, right?
That's at least more מענטשקייט. mentshkayt. You don't want to start interviewing
for the next job before you've told somebody that they're fired. That
is very, you know, undermining and very highly offensive. So that's sort
of the difference. You start with the one that you're removing the
קדושה kedusha from, that's okay. But if you start with the other
one, that's sort of inappropriate and also that is what gives it
the קדושה kedusha of the first. So now let's take a look
at the גמרא Gemara as it focuses on this language. למימרא, Lemeimra,
to tell you תחת tachat לשנא דאתפוסי הוא, lishna de'atpusei hu, that
תחת tachat is a language of תמורה temurah and it's a language
of אתפוסי. atpusei. Now the גמרא Gemara to contrast to a language
of מחולל, mechulal, of redeeming and removing from the word חולין, chullin,
de-sanctifying the first, uses the phrase to describe, conceptualize what the phrase
of תמורה temurah uses, the word of אתפוסי. atpusei. What does אתפוסי
atpusei mean? תפוס, Tafus, to grab. Because what happens is is it
gets grabbed by the קדושה kedusha of the first. You're not removing
the קדושה kedusha of the first, it gets grabbed by the קדושה
kedusha of the first. Of course you're not trying to make them
both קדוש, kadosh, you're trying to exchange, but still the language the
גמרא Gemara uses is it's a language of grabbing rather than a
language of de-sanctifying. Okay, so that sounds like what you're saying תחת
tachat is, but is that really so clear? רמינהו, Reminehu, I'll ask
you on this. קדשי בדק הבית, Kodshei bedek habayit, let's say you
have something that's not תמורה, temurah, not in the category of תמורה,
temurah, just sanctified for the temple treasury. And what you're trying to
do is basically exchange one thing for another. Somebody sanctified, you know,
to his Ford, you don't need that, so you're trying to swap
it in for who knows what, you know, so here, so what
language do you use? So if you say חליפת זו, chalifat zo,
תמורת זו, tmurat zo, לא אמר כלום. lo amar klum. If you
said an exchange for this, an exchange for that, you didn't say
anything because again you're not removing the קדושה kedusha from the first
item. Now you don't transgress תמורה, temurah, תמורה temurah is only by
קרבנות, korbanot, but you haven't done an effective transferring of the קדושה
kedusha because you haven't focused on removing it from the first item.
If you say תחת זו, tachat zo, מחוללת על זו, mechulelet al
zo, דבריו קיימין. devarav kayamin. In exchange for, under this, or it
is redeemed on that, then it works. So redeemed we understand, that's
our משנה, Mishnah, you focus by removing the קדושה. kedusha. But here
תחת tachat in this ברייתא braita is working differently than in our
משנה. Mishnah. תחת Tachat here is working in the same way as
מחולל, mechulal, that it's understood that you're removing it from A, not
that you are bringing B into the ambit of A.
So it all depends on your context then.
So that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. So let's
take a look. ואי סלקא דעתך לשנא דאתפוסי היא, Ve'i salka da'atach
lishna de'atpusei hi, if תחת tachat is a language more of being
grabbed, not of de-sanctifying, מאי שנא רישא מאי שנא סיפא? mai shna
reisha mai shna seifa? Why is it in the, you know, why
is it that in the beginning of the משנה Mishnah here that
תחת tachat means language of תמורה temurah and in this case of
בדק הבית bedek habayit תחת tachat means a language of redemption? So
the גמרא Gemara says אמר אביי, amar Abaye, תחת משכחת לה לשנא
דאתפוסי ולשנא דאחולי. tachat meshkachat lah lishna de'atpusei ulishna de'achulei. תחת Tachat
has both senses, a sense of sort of being grabbed and a
sense of being de-sanctified and redeeming. לשנא דאתפוסי דכתיב, Lishna de'atpusei dechtiv,
so now we have to find a source. So where do you
have the sense that תחת tachat can mean grabbed? Right? So where
do you get the sense that it can mean being grabbed? Because
it says ואם תחתיה תעמוד הבהרת. ve'im tachteha ta'amod habaheret. So this
is about צרעת, tzara'at, and it says if the spot of leprosy
stays in its place, תחתיה tachteha meaning your תחת, tachat, you know,
you're in your, you remain in place. תחת Tachat like underneath you,
you stay, you know, you sit on your תחת, tachat, you stay
in your place. So that's תחתיה. tachteha. So that's a language of
אתפוסי. atpusei. Why is it a language of אתפוסי? atpusei? Because it's
not a language of removing its status. תחתיה Tachteha there means you're
staying in your place. Okay, so therefore תחת tachat does not always
have that context of removing. things from something, it could be that
the thing is staying in its place and it's as we see
here. Okay, and it also לשנא דאחולי lishna d'achulei and how you
have this idea of sort of removing from one and giving to
the other, כתיב תחת הנחשת אביא זהב, ksiv tachas hanechoshes avi zahav,
in exchange for the copper I will bring gold. So therefore it
means that you remove sort of the copper and you put gold
in its place. So that's the sense of redemption. הלכך גבי קדשי
מזבח דעבדין תמורה, hilkach gabi kodshei mizbeach d'avdin tmura, when it comes
to sacrifices that the concept of תמורה tmura is relevant, so לשנא
דאתפוסי lishna d'atpusei he will read it in the language of of
seizing and not of desanctifying. Okay, and therefore it'll be a תמורה.
tmura. גבי קדשי בדק הבית דלא עבדין תמורה, gabi kodshei bedek habayis
d'lo avdin tmura, by קדשי בדק הבית kodshei bedek habayis that תמורה
tmura is an irrelevant concept because you don't have it by temple
treasury, לשנא דאחולי lishna d'achulei he will read it as redemption and
it will work. There's a little bit of a problem though. The
problem is, and the גמרא gemara will get sort of not really
get to this but it'll sort of you know indirectly address this
tomorrow, is but by translating it as תמורה tmura where it's relevant,
we basically mean that make you have transgressed, we cause you to
have sinned by translating that way, right? And we cause the second
animal to become קדוש. kadosh. So it's not just oh you know
oh it's convenient so let's say it works wherever it can work.
Working is a bad thing by תמורה. tmura. So you have to
read אביי Abaye not just that we're like we're choosing to do
that but we but contextually we assume that that's sort of what
you meant in that context. Although again it's not really so clear
why we should assume that, you know? So the גמרא gemara will
go on tomorrow and say that there are times where we'll be
more inclined to read תחת tachas in a way that doesn't make
you transgress, in a way that's actually the language of redemption rather
than in the way that's the language of תמורה tmura which is
the problematic language. Okay, so we'll continue tomorrow.